A Guide to the Anna P. Sokolina Architectural Collection, 1924-2017
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Anna P. Sokolina Architectural Collection, 1924-2017
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Sokolina, Anna P.
Ms2002-051
5.2 Cubic Feet 8 boxes; 2 oversize folders
Anna P. Sokolina is an architectural historian. The majority of the collection consists of her publications, professional documentation, conferences participation, exhibit catalogs, teaching materials, and materials related to her involvement in the International Archive of Women in Architecture.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Anna P. Sokolina Architectural Collection was donated to the IAWA at Special Collections in June 2002 by its creator. Additions were made to the collection in October 2003, November 2005, and October 2007.
Biographical Information
Anna Sokolina was born in St. Petersburg (Leningrad). In 1980 she received her Masters in Architecture degree from the Moscow Architectural Institute and in 1992 her Ph.D. from the Russian Academic Research Institute for the Theory of Architecture and Urban Design. In 2001, Sokolina completed the Certificate Program in Arts Administration at New York University SCPS Department of Arts, Sciences and Humanities. She interned at the Art Commission of the City of New York; the Cooper-Hewitt National Design Museum, Smithsonian Institution; and the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum New York.
Since 1986, Sokolina has worked on various architectural exhibitions. The first, entitled "Concepts of Soviet Architecture 1917-1987" held in West Berlin, was developed by the Central Academic Research Institute for the Theory of Architecture and Urban Design in partnership with the Shchusev Museum of Architecture in Moscow and the Janus Foundation in Berlin. Following the fall of the USSR, Sokolina worked on international exhibitions for the Moscow Young Architects Association. In 1992-93, she curated traveling exhibitions "New Architectural Concepts from Moscow" at Green Berlin Hall, Germany, and at the Ecole d'Architecture de Strasbourg, France; and in 1994, "Art Russia" at the Gallery Buergerhaus (City Hall) Groebenzell, Germany. Sokolina was also the curator/director of the Tabakman Museum in Hudson, NY. Her responsibilities included: the inauguration of the museum's eight galleries totaling 9,000 square feet, several permanent exhibitions and an art shop. From 1996-99 as an independent curator, Sokolina organized art exhibitions at the Steiner Foundation in Harlemville, NY, the New York Open Center in Soho, and at the American Education Center in Rego Park, NY. From 2000-2002 Sokolina was co-curator to a touring exhibition "Journeys of the Imagination: From the former Soviet Union to the United States" at Exhibits USA, Mid-America Arts Alliance. She volunteers for the Metropolitan Museum of Art's Education Department.
Sokolina has also edited a monographic anthology, Architecture and Anthroposophy, in which twenty-seven distinguished subject specialists wrote chapters on philosophically and spiritually inspired trends in organic architecture and art of the 20th century. In 2002 Sokolina started working on a collaborative non-profit project, Russian Art 1860-1940 in Western Collections, Information Database on the Internet funded by a number of donors including the S.R. Guggenheim Foundation, the Ministry of Culture of the Russian Federation, the Judith Rothschild Foundation, and Galerie Gmurzynska in Cologne. The project aims to develop a web-based bilingual database of information on Russian art to serve as a resource for educational and scholarly research, and for national and international exchange of knowledge. As of 2007, Sokolina is an assistant professor at the Architecture and Interior Design at Miami University in Ohio.
Scope and Content
The majority of the collection consists of publications written by Anna Sokolina featured in books, magazines and newspapers in Germany, Russia, and the United States. The collection also contains her professional documentation, conferences in which Sokolina participated, and some conference papers that Sokolina was invited to present. The collection also includes catalogs from exhibitions that she curated while working at various museums starting in 1997, materials related to her involvement as honorary advisor to the International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA), syllabi, teaching materials, dissertation, thesis, research, and artwork.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged five series, each of which is arranged in chronological order.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Material
The following items - a poetry book, doctoral dissertation three books by Sokolina and two containing chapters by Sokolina - were cataloged in the on-line library catalog Addison and transferred to the Rare Book Collection:
Arkhitektura Zapada. [Ocherki] Red. Kollegi'i'a: S.O. Khan-Magomedov (otv. red.) [i dr.]. [Moscow]: Stroǐizdat, 1972-1987. (Sokolina has chapter, "Charles Moore: Theory and Practice") Call number: NA680 .A76
Problemy istorii arkhitektury: tezisy dokladov: vseso'i'uzna'i'a nauchna'i'a konferen't'si'i'a, Suzdal'. Moscow: VNIITAG Goskomarkhitektury, 1990. (Sokolina has 3-page portion, "The Concept of Tradition in East German Architecture, 1945-1990") Call number: NA190 .P76 1990
Sokolina, Anna. Osvoenie tradi't'siǐ v arkhitekture GDR: teori'i'a i istor i'ia arkhitektury restavra't'si'ia pam'iatnikov arkhitektury. 1991. (doctoral dissertation) Call number: NA1089 .S65 1991
Sokolina, Anna. Stikhi (Poems), New York: TELEX, 1998. Call number: PG3549.S63 S75 1998
Index Terms
Persons:
Sokolina, Anna P.
Subjects:
History of Women in Architecture; International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA); Women -- History
Contents LIst
- Biographical Information, 2002-2007
  - Biographical Information, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Brief biography, Curriculum vitae, Lists of publications, exhibit catalogs, talks at conferences, and exhibitions
  - Biographical Information, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Brief biography, Curriculum vitae, Lists of publications, exhibit catalogs, lectures and talks at conferences, and exhibitions
  - Biographical Information - Miami University, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Faculty listing from website, Listings in Miami U. newsletters, Curriculum vitae, Lists of publications, exhibit catalogs, talks at conferences, and exhibitions
- Publications and Conference Participation, 1980-2011
  - Výstavba a Architektura (periodical in Czech), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    "The Basic Contradictions of Postmodernism," August 1980
  - Architektura by the Union of Architects in the USSR (newspaper in Russian), 1981-1983 (Oversize 1)
    "Metaphors of Arata Isozuki," 1981; "The Search of the Origins," 1982; "Ironies of Charles Moore," 1983
  - APX6 - Architecture in the USSR (periodical in Russian), 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    "Hermann Henselmann," November-December 1987
  - AC - Arkhitektura i stroitel stvo Rossii (Russian Architecture and Construction) (periodical in Russian), 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    "Residential Construction in East Germany: The Experiments of the 1980s," May 1989; Book Review, February 1990; "The Ground Floor of the City," July 1990; "Ralf Niebergall," November 1990
  - Architecture and Urban Design - Industrial Construction (periodical in Russian), 1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    "Industrial Interpretation of Traditions: Urban Design of the 1980s in East Germany," Special Issue #3, 1990
  - Conference Report, International Architectural Conference in Jarna, Sweden, July 1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    "Die Neue Freiheit" (The New Freedom)
  - Stadt Bauwelt (periodical in German), 1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    "Von der Papierarchitektur zum Joint venture" (From Paper Architecture to Joint Venture), Dec. 28, 1992
  - Kommune (periodical in German), 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    "Die lange Krise der Architektur in Russland" (The Long Crisis in Russian Architecture), Oct. 1992; "Rußland nach dem Umbruch" (Russia after the Upheaval), Oct. 1993; "Ökologische Tendenzen in der russischen Architektur" (The Ecological Approach in Russian Architecture), Jan. 1994
  - Newsletter Man and Architecture (in German and English), 1992, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    "Die neue Freiheit: Nachgedanken zu Järna aus Moskau" Nov. 1992; "Jürg Spörri, Architekt, oder Nachprüfung der Vorliebe," July 1994
  - Conference program and paper, European Academy of the Urban Environment (UNESCO), Berlin, Germany, May 1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    "Paper Architects and Secret Architecture: Planning and Building in the Crisis in Russia"
  - Ambiente (periodical in German), 1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    "Russlands Architekten verbünden sich" (Moscow's Architects Unite), Sept. 1993
  - Der Architekt (periodical in German), 1994, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    "Wohnen in Moskau" (Living in Moscow), Feb. 1994; "Moskau nach dem Umbruch" (Moscow after the Upheaval), Feb. 1994; "Ökologische Tendenzen in der Architektur" (Ecological Trends in Architecture), Feb. 1994; "Architektur-Galerien in Manhattan," (Architectural Galleries in Manhattan), June 1996
  - Novoye Russkoye Slovo (New Russian Word) (Russian-American newspaper in Russian), 1996 (Oversize 1)
    "Paper Architecture," Vol. 87, No. 30.115, February 3-4, 1996
  - New Yorkskiye Sezony (The New York Seasons) (Russian-American periodical in Russian), 1997 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    "The Tabakman Museum," Vol. 3, No. 2, June 1997
  - Slovo-Word (periodical in Russian), 1997 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    "Architecture and Anthroposophy," No. 21, 1997
  - Book, Poems, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bulletin of the Society of Historians of East European and Russian Art and Architecture (SHERA), eight selected issues, 1999-2003 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Most of the issues have references to Sokolina's professional activities
  - Reviews of and references about Sokolina's book Architecture and Anthroposophy, various authors, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - ARTMARGINS: Contemporary central and eastern European visual culture (online periodical) - Selected print-outs of web site archives containing articles by or about Sokolina (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Essay, "Alternative Identities: Conceptual Transformations in Soviet and Post-Soviet Architecture", April 2001
    - Roundtable response to "What is the single most important change to have occurred in East-Central European art since the fall of Communism?"
    - Review of Sokolina's book, "What Do Architecture and Anthroposophy Have in Common?" by Wm. Craft Brumfield, March 2004
    - Essay, "In Opposition to the State: The Soviet Neoavant-Grade and East German Aestheticism in the 1980s", May 2002
    - Review of conference "East-European Art and Architecture in the 20th Century" held at MIT in Oct. 2001 by Juliana Maxim and Mark Jarzombek
    - Review, "Database on Russian Art, 1860-1940", Dec. 2003
    - Review, "The Canon Divided: New Identities Versus the Universal Dream", June 2003
    - Review, "Eye on Malevich: An Epoch Revisited", April 2004
    - Review, "Debating Russian Art: Two Panel Discussions," (RUSSIA! at the Guggenheim), Dec. 2005
  - The Anthropology of East Europe Review: Central Europe, Eastern Europe and Eurasia, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    "Architecture and the State: Moscow Urban Concepts After Socialism," Vol. 2, No. 2, Autumn 2002
  - Poster for lecture for IAWA, Oct. 2003 (Oversize 1)
    "Conflicting Visions of National Perspective in Contemporary Russian Architecture"
  - AV (Arkhitekturnyi vestnik) (periodical in Russian), No. 3, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Review of Sokolina's book by Prof. Vladimir L. Khait; First Russian architectural publication to publish the IAWA call for submissions
  - Lecture with CCCP Exhibit, June 2007, and Symposium talk for IAWA, Oct. 2007 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    "Architecture as Collateral Damage: Was Memorials and the Rebirth of Patriotism in Soviet Russia"; Web site description of CCCP lecture; Outline for IAWA talk with images used for illustration
  - Memorials for Milka Bliznakov written by Sokolina (periodicals in English and Russian), 2011 (Box 2)
  - Poster advertising IAWA talk (Oversize 1)
- Exhibition Participation and Curatorial Work, 1982-2005
  - Catalog, The Exhibition of Art Works by Moscow's Architects March-April 1982, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Includes images of 20 art works by Sokolina; Exhibition Notice, "70th Anniversary of the Great October," anniversary exhibition by Architect's Union of the USSR held in the People's House of Friendship, Moscow, 1987
  - Posters, Moskauer Architekten (Moscow Architects: Architecture and Art Exhibition) held in Gröbenzell, Germany, curated by Sokolina, Jan. 1994 (Oversize 1)
  - Catalogs from The Tabakman Museum of Contemporary Russian Art, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Young Russia, March 1997; Evgeny Mikhnov Voitenko, May 1997; Valery Yurlov (Sokolina co-wrote catalog), June 1997
  - Catalogs of Traveling Exhibitions from Exhibits USA, 2000-2001, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Catalog entries for "Journeys of the Imagination: From the Former Soviet Union to the United States" with curators Anna Sokolina and Jennifer Cahn, 2000-2001
  - Submission application with color image of artwork, Metropolitan Museum of Art, Employee Art Show, 2003, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- IAWA Materials, 2003-2017, n.d.
  - Information about Russian women architects (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Correspondence with Russian women architects and with IAWA, 2002-2007; Mailing list of Russian women architects, their heirs, and architectural institutions, 2007; List of gifts to the IAWA from Russian women architects and Sokolina, 2007
  - Annual Reports for the Board of Advisors Meeting, 2003, 2004, 2007, 2011-2012 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - IAWA Honorary Board Advisor, 2016 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - IAWA Symposia posters, 2016-2017 (Box 8)
- Teaching Information, 2006-2008, n.d.
  - Syllabi for 5 classes taught at Miami University and departmental semester course schedule, 2006-2007 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Introduction to Studio Design (2 classes); Independent Studies: Alternative Architecture; Russian Art and Architecture II: From 1860 to Present; Russian Art and Architecture I: From Byzantine Period to 1860
  - Poster advertising class (Oversize 1)
  - Syllabi for 2 classes taught at Yale Summer Session, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Russian Art and Architecture I: From Byzantine Period to 1860; Russian Art and Architecture II: From 1860 to Present
- Professional Papers, 1924-2010
  - Lev Nikolaevich Avdotjin, 1979-1990 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Anna Shchetinina, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Weekly News Bulletin: Published by the press section of the society for Cultural Relations with Foreign Countries no. 42-44, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Moscow Building, 23-24, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Soviet Architecture, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Worker's Housing: the Moscow Soviet of Workers', Peasants', and Soldiers' Deputies, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Performance of the Council of People's Commissars and Orgburo on July 10, 1935: on the General Plan of Reconstruction of Moscow, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Anna Sokolina: Graphics, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Evolution of Public Centers Towns of Antiquity, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Russian Art: the Second Half of the 20th Century and the Beginning of the 21st Century Abroad, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Dissertation Research Manuscripts, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Academisn Notes, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Thesis 1-2 Vol., Authoreferat, 12 Neg., 1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Diploma, Thesis, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Biscuit: Order of Lenin's Bolshevik Confectionary, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Biscuit: Order of Lenin's Bolshevik Confectionary, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Problems of Architecture: Materials Collection Book 1, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Art & Artifacts, 1974-1995, n.d.
  - 14 Drawings on Paper - Undergraduate and Graduate, n.d. (Box 5)
  - 5 Gouaches on Paper 21 ½"x 29 ½" (55 cm x75 cm), 1975-1976 (Box 6)
  - 2 Comparative Tables of Masterplans on Craft Paper 24"x34", 1978 (Box 7)
  - Study Presented on 2 Comparative Tables on Craft Paper 40" x 40" (1m x 1m), n.d. (Box 7)
  - Drawings, 1974-1979 (Oversize 1)
  - Paintings, 1974-1980, 1988, 1995 (Box 5)
  - Analytical Presentation Boards for Defense of Doctoral Thesis, 1992 (Oversize 1, Oversize 2)